A Guide to the Auditor of Public Accounts, Capitol Square Data, Records, 1776-1971
Library of Virginia
- Series II: Grounds, 1776-1931
  - Deeds (Photostats), 1785-1862 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Earthmoving and Landscaping Contract, 1817-1820 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Executive Papers
    - Gov. James Barber - 1812 March 27
  - Fence
    - Contract, 1817-1819 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Proposals, 1816-1817 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - General Estimate of Public Buildings, Undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Inquisitions
    - 1781-1788 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1781-1791 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Photostat Volume, 1781-1788
  - Legislative History of Capitol Square, 1852 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Lots, 1836 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Receipts, 1817-1819 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Reservoir, 1827 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Stonework Contracts
    - Kinkead, James, 1817-1819 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Longden, George C., 1817-1820 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Vouchers
    - 1819 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1820 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1825-1827 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Series III: Statues, 1784-1932
  This series relates to statues on Capitol Square and elsewhere in the City of Richmond. Volume 3 of the Capitol Square Data includes documents regarding the history and value of the Houdon Statue from 1873, a bronze copy of Houdon's statue of Washington for France in 1910, the Washington Monument Fund and architect Robert Mills, and a biography of Thomas Crawford in 1908, artist for the Equestrian Statue of Washington. For additional records on the Equestrian Statue of Washington, researchers should consult the Washington Monument Fund (APA 668).
  The Executive Papers of Gov. Joseph Johnson include a petition from twelve members of the General Assembly regarding plaster casts of the Houdon Statue to be placed in state colleges and a letter concerning the same from W.J. Hubard to George W. Munford, Secretary of the Commonwealth. Lastly, there is a letter and receipt from G. Blagden to Joseph Huddlestone regarding an inscription engraved on the pedestal of the Houdon Statue in 1813.
  - Capitol Square Data, Vol. 3: Statues
    - Pages 1-90 - Houdon's Statue of Washington, 1784-1931 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Pages 91-95 - La Fayette, 1784 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Pages 96-134 - Equestrian Statue of Washington, 1816-1908 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Pages 135-138 - Henry Clay, 1860-1932 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Pages 139-150 - Stonewall Jackson, 1875-1877 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Pages 151-153 - Lee Monument, 1887-1903 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Pages 154-155 - Dr. Hunter Holmes McGuire, 1901-1902 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Pages 156-160 - J.E.B. Stuart, 1903 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Pages 161-163 - Governor William Smith, 1904-1931 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Pages 164-165 - Captain John Smith, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Pages 166-181 - Other Statues in Capitol Building, 1931-1932 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Bibliography, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Capitol Square Data, Vol. 3: Statues (Photocopy), 1784-1932
  - Houdon Statue of Washington
    - Executive Papers - Gov. Joseph Johnson, 1854 Feb. 10 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Inscription, 1813 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Superintendent of Public Buildings, 1798-1906
  This series documents the work of the Superintendent of Public Buildings and its various incarnations including Superintendent of Public Edifices, the Superintendent for the Improvement of the Public Square, etc. This series mostly consists of reports of the Superintendent from 1819 until 1850. These reports to the governor provide the best narrative on the work done to Capitol Square during this time period. The reports relate to a variety of subjects including leaks in the Capitol Building, repairs, the Bell Tower, the Governor's Stable and Mansion, Museum, etc. In addition to public buildings, the reports also concern arms and ammunition, the Public Guard, and the Armory. Noteworthy is a report of 15 June 1841 which includes a drawing of the Capitol Building depicting the skylight. During this time, several individuals served as Superintendent including Claiborne W. Gooch, Adjutant General (1819-1820); Capt. Blair Bolling, Superintendent of Public Property/Edifices (1821-1839); Lt. E. Brown, Public Guard (1839); John B. Richardson, Superintendent of Public Buildings (1839-1843); and Charles Dimmock, Superintendent of Public Buildings (1844-1850).
  This series also contains applications and recommendations to Gen. W.C. Newberry, while he served as Superintendent of Public Buildings. These records, which date between 1869 and 1872, document individuals' requests for positions in Capitol Square including Capitol Police, janitors, watchmen, and others.
  Orris Paine, was appointed by Governor Wilson Cary Nicholas in July 1816 as Superintendent relative to the repairing of the Capitol, improving the Public Square, and building the Governor's stable. Paine kept files containing account books, correspondence, accounts, and receipts. Paine often wrote the Governor with respect to repairs to the Capitol, accounts, and other topics. The correspondence also includes memos of agreement with A.S. Brockenbrough who served as Superintendent of the Improvement of the Public Square.
  Two files labeled "miscellaneous" contain contracts, correspondence, accounts, receipts, vouchers, etc., between 1874 and 1879. These documents seem to originate from the Register of the Land Office who also served as Superintendent of Public Buildings beginning in 1874. These materials relate to sundry purchases, roofing the State Courthouse, renting the old Armory Building, furnishing coal for state buildings, and purchasing boilers for the Capitol Building from the Tredegar Iron Works.
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1882-1906 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Executive Papers - Gov. James Wood, 1798 Feb. 8 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1874 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1875-1879 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Newberry, William C. - Applications, Recommendations, etc.
    - 1869-1870 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1871-1872 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Paine, Orris
    - Account Books, 1816-1818 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Accounts and Receipts, 1816-1821 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1817-1820 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - General Accounts and Settlements, 1816-1819 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Reports
    - 1819-1820 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1821 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1822 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1823 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1824 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1825 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - 1826 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - 1827 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - 1828 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - 1829 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - 1830 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - 1831 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - 1832 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - 1833 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - 1836 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - 1837 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - 1838 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - 1839 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - 1840 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - 1841 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - 1842 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - 1843-1844 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - 1845 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - 1846 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - 1848-1850 (Box 11, Folder 25)
- Oversized - Series I: Buildings
  - Subseries A: Capitol Building
    - Vouchers - Numbered - Account, 1787-1790 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Vouchers - Unnumbered, 1795 July 21 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Vouchers - Unnumbered, 1855-1856 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Subseries B: Governor's Mansion
    - Inventories, 1849, Jan. 9 and 30 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Vouchers, 1797-1856 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Subseries C: Other Buildings
    - Library Heating System - Blueprints, 1906 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Oversized - Series II: Grounds
  - Clarke Property - Map, 1857 June 25 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Inquisitions, Abstract of Inquisitions, 1876 Nov. 6 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Inquisitions - Turpin, Philip (Lot #762) 1788 May 31 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Oversized - Series IV: Superintendent of Public Buildings
  - Paine, Orris
    - Correspondence, 1819 March 18 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - General Accounts and Settlements, 1816 Nov. 6 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - General Accounts and Settlements, 1817 Nov. 5 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - General Accounts and Settlements, 1817 Dec. (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - General Accounts and Settlements, 1817 Dec. (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - General Accounts and Settlements, 1818 Jan. 30 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Reports - Clinton's Thermo-Hydrometer, 1842 (Box 12, Folder 16)